Today's דף daf we're up to is צדי ב, Tzadi Beis, which
is the beginning of the next פרק, perek, but yesterday we did
not complete צדי א, Tzadi Alef, the last פרק, perek, so we're
going to wrap that up so we'll be able to, so we'll
start with a little אגדתא. aggadeta. So we pick up on צדי
א Tzadi Alef עמוד ב Amud Beis about four lines before the
lines get to be the middle size, so four lines at the
end of the first of the narrow ones, at the two dots.
כתיב. Ksiv. So this was a discussion about, you know, about it
started with a whole issue of weight and measures, and then it
became about trying to manipulate the market and corner the market, and
not to, particularly around staples and around certain food staples, and then
about not, if you're involved in buying and selling as a middleman
for staples, again particularly for food, particularly also with a heightened concern
in Israel, then a limit about how much profit that you can
make. And with that we got into the whole discussion about מחלון
וכליון Machlon v'Chilyon and אלימלך, Elimelech, and they left Israel at a
time of famine,
and that, you know, and that they, one of the explanations about
why they were punished was because they abandoned the people, and you're
not supposed to leave Israel even in difficult times unless it's really,
there's really no choice in terms of the issue of the food
and so on. So now the גמרא Gemara picks up, כתיב, Ksiv,
again four lines before the lines get middle-sized here on צדי א
Tzadi Alef עמוד ב. Amud Beis. כתיב מחלון וכליון. Ksiv Machlon v'Chilyon.
So the פסוק pasuk in רות Rus calls them מחלון וכליון. Machlon
v'Chilyon. וכתיב, U'ksiv, and when their names are listed in דברי הימים,
Divrei Hayamim, it calls them יואש ושרף. Yoash v'Saraf. So both of
those names, sets of names, are very like evocative, you know, and
about destruction and so on. So let's take a look. But anyway,
it gives them different names. רב ושמואל. Rav v'Shmuel. So it's a
debate of רב ושמואל. Rav v'Shmuel. חד אמר, Chad amar, one says,
מחלון וכליון שמן. Machlon v'Chilyon shman. Their given names were מחלון וכליון.
Machlon v'Chilyon. ולמה נקרא שמן יואש ושרף? V'lama nikru shman Yoash v'Saraf?
Why were they called
יואש
ושרף? Yoash v'Saraf? יואש, Yoash, שנתייאשו מן הגאולה. shenisyashu min hageulah. יואש
Yoash because they gave up hope from redemption as they left the
land of Israel. שרף, Saraf, ונתחייבו שריפה למקום, v'shenischayev s'reifah lamakom, and
burning because they were deserving of being burned and destroyed because of
this, because of their sin of abandoning the people and the land.
וחד אמר, V'chad amar, יואש ושרף שמן. Yoash v'Saraf shman. No, their
given name was יואש ושרף. Yoash v'Saraf. ולמה נקרא שמן מחלון וכליון?
V'lama nikru shman Machlon v'Chilyon? So why were they called מחלון וכליון?
Machlon v'Chilyon? מחלון, Machlon, שעשו גופן חולין. she'asu gufan chulin. מחלון Machlon
because from the word חולין, chulin, they made themselves,
desacralized themselves, which the רשב"ם Rashbam says means because they left ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. They were willing to go to חוץ לארץ. chutz
la'aretz. Actually if you think of the abbreviations of חוץ לארץ, chutz
la'aretz, חית וו למד ches vav lamed is חו"ל. chul. Right, חולין.
chulin. That's what they call it in Israel. You're going to חו"ל.
chul. So anyway, they made themselves חולין. chulin. וכליון, V'chilyon, שנתחייבו כליה
למקום. shenischayvu klayah lamakom. They were deserving of destruction. תניא כמאן דאמר
מחלון וכליון שמן. Tanya k'man d'amar Machlon v'Chilyon shman. We taught a
ברייתא braisa according to the approach that their given name was מחלון
וכליון. Machlon v'Chilyon. דתניא, Detanya, מאי דכתיב, mai d'ksiv, what's meant, ויוקים
ואנשי
כוזיבא ויואש ושרף אשר בעלו למואב ויושבי לחם והדברים עתיקים. v'Yokim v'anshei
Chozeva v'Yoash v'Saraf asher ba'alu l'Moav v'yoshvei Lechem v'hadvarim attikim. So
that's a nice very cryptic verse. Seems to list a couple of
people or whatever. ויוקים Yokim and the people of כוזיבא Chozeva and
יואש ושרף Yoash v'Saraf who had sexual relations with מואב Moav and
those who dwell in לחם, Lechem, and they are ancient words. Right,
very easy, very transparent פסוק pasuk there. So now the גמרא Gemara
is going to parse it. ויוקים, V'Yokim, זה יהושע. zeh Yehoshua. That
refers to יהושע, Yehoshua, שהקים שבועה לאנשי גבעון, shehikim shavuah l'anshei Giv'on,
that he established his oath, he made a promise to the people
of גבעון, Giv'on, right, who had disguised themselves as if they were,
you know, coming from a far away land, and he made that
שבועה shavuah to them. ואנשי כוזיבא, V'anshei Chozeva, אלו אנשי גבעון, elu
anshei Giv'on, those are the people of גבעון, Giv'on, שכזבו ביהושע, shekizvu
b'Yehoshua, that they, they deceived him or and they did not keep
up of their end of the oath. ויואש ושרף, V'Yoash v'Saraf, why
are they all listed in the same פסוק? pasuk? So the רשב"ם
Rashbam says the context of the פסוק pasuk are descendants of יהודה.
Yehudah. Now of course we don't know that certainly אנשי כוזיבא, anshei
Chozeva, גבעון Giv'on are not, but even יהושע Yehoshua we don't know,
right, יהושע Yehoshua is not a, he's not from the tribe of
יהודה. Yehudah. But he says well, maybe through his mother, I'll tell
you in a minute what the מהרש"א Maharsha says about this.
Anyway, keep on going,
where are
we? אשר בעלו למואב, Asher ba'alu l'Moav, that they had sex with
מואב, Moav, שנשאו נשים מואביות. shenasu nashim Moaviyot. Okay, that actually works
you know well in the context, right, they married these Moabite women.
ויושבי לחם, V'yoshvei Lechem, and those who dwell in
לחם, Lechem, like בית לחם, Beis Lechem, זו רות המואביה zo Rus
HaMoaviya ששבה ונדבקה sheshava v'nidbeka to יושבי, yoshvei, not just to dwell
but שבה. shava. returned and נדבקה בבית לחם, ve-nidbekah be-Beit Lechem, okay,
בבית לחם יהודה. be-Beit Lechem Yehudah. והדברים עתיקים, Ve-hadvarim atikim, the words
are ancient, דברים הללו עתיק יומין אמרן. devarim halalu Atik Yomin amran.
These things the ancient of days God had already predicted this or
you know from the very beginning. כדכתיב kidechtiv as it says, מצאתי
דוד עבדי, matzati David avdi, I have found David my servant. So
sort of so connecting David with the word מצא. matza. וכתיב ve-chtiv
and it says, שתי בנותיך הנמצאות, shtei bnotecha hanimtzot, your two daughters
who are found here take them out of the city with Lot.
So God had already sort of planned that David would be descendant
from the daughters of Moab, it all goes back to you know
God's hand in history from way back. Okay, so anyway, so what
so there we have we've proven מחלון וכליון. Machlon ve-Chilion. What do
we get from this putting them in the same פסוק? pasuk? So
the מהרש״א Maharsha says very nicely, he says that the point of
this פסוק pasuk is going back and it's re-underscoring this question about
maintaining the faith, right? And to what degree did the you know
because the whole point is מחלון וכליון, Machlon ve-Chilion, they did not
retain their faith in God, in the people. They abandoned the people,
they abandoned the land, they abandoned God, they went to this foreign
land. And he says in here, you know, יהושע, Yehoshua, so if
you take a look at like יהושע Yehoshua and אנשי גבעון, Anshei
Givon, you know, even though יהושע Yehoshua kept to this oath he
made to אנשי גבעון, Anshei Givon, even though they had deceived him,
he, like it's contrasting then, he had kept to this oath, right,
he had maintained the faith. רות Rut who even came from a
foreign land, right, was willing to go ahead and you know and
go to this and you know and go to this land to
contrast the acts of מחלון וכליון Machlon ve-Chilion from the people that
are sort of you know maintain the faith and to the you
know and you know and you know to the of the oaths
that they made to the people, to the
land and so on. The מהרש״א, Maharsha, the רב יעקב עמדין Rav
Yaakov Emden also makes another interesting comparison contrast. He says all the
people here were people that were sort of dealing with issues you
know that married non-Jewish women. יהושע, Yehoshua, yeah, so he says יהושע
Yehoshua is right, right, according to the מדרש, Midrash, יהושע Yehoshua married
רחב, Rachav, okay. And and רות Rut of course, I mean בועז
Boaz married רות. Rut. אנשי גבעון? Anshei Givon?
Well, those are the people of גבעון. Givon.
Because they were Jewish at the beginning?
Yeah, I don't know exactly, I forget exactly how he reads it
in. But anyway, but he says the point is all of them
did it only like the היתר heter after they converted, right, and
whereas you know whereas מחלון וכליון Machlon ve-Chilion did it באיסור. be-issur.
But anyway, so there is a big contrast that are being made
here between the people in this פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so now that
we've quoted these פסוקים pesukim about מחלון וכליון Machlon ve-Chilion in דברי
הימים, Divrei HaYamim, we're going to continue. המה היוצרים ויושבי נטעים וגדרה
עם המלך במלאכתו ישבו שם. Hemah hayotzrim viyoshvei neta'im ve-gederah im ha-melech
bimlachto yashvu sham.
Okay, what the heck that means? They are the fashioners who dwell
amongst the plantings and whatever and fenced with the king in his
work. All right, so ישבו שם yashvu sham who dwell there. המה
היוצרים, Hemah hayotzrim, אלו בני יונדב בן רכב, שנטרו שבועת אביהם. elu
bnei Yonadav ben Rechav shenatzru shvu'at avihem
So this also is very much about maintaining the oath, maintaining the
faith in contrast to מחלון וכליון. Machlon ve-Chilion. So if you read
the story in ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, which I had to remind refresh myself
of, God basically says go take these people the descendants of רכב
Rechav and רכב Rechav you know רכב Rechav you know which are
and you know bring them into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash into
a room there and offer them some wine. So ירמיהו Yirmiyahu does
that and he offers them some wine and they say, no, we
can't drink any wine because this is what our father made us
take this oath you
know be whatever you know the father of our nation, of our
people before many many generations that we would never drink wine and
that we would never buy land and that we would remain nomads
and so on and we've been keeping this oath you know until
this day. And then God basically uses them as a contrast to
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael who have you know not kept their faith
with God and that's why they're going to go into גלות galut
and so on. Now because of רכב, Rechav, right, it's associated with
you know it's assumed here to be read as descendants of יתרו.
Yitro. So the גמרא Gemara says right one of the names of
יתרו. Yitro. So it says רכב? Rechav? Yeah, that's according to the
מדרש Midrash it associates רכב Rechav and בני רכב bnei Rechav here
with יתרו. Yitro.
That's what I said like seven names, רכב Rechav wasn't one of
them.
I think it was.
יתרו יתר רעואל חובב חבר קיני פוטיאל. Yitro Yeter Reuel Chovav Chever
Keni Putiel.
Oh, that's very impressive.
Okay, anyway, I thought I think according to one it is associated
with יתרו, Yitro, but anyway, but maybe not. But anyway המה hemah
anyway, let's take a look. המה
היוצרים, Hemah hayotzrim, okay, so אלו בני יונדב בן רכב elu bnei
Yonadav ben Rechav, שנטרו שבועת אביהם shenatzru shvu'at avihem. that they kept
the oath, they kept again here's the people that kept the faith.
ויושבי נטעים, Viyoshvei neta'im, זה שלמה, ze Shlomo, שדומה לנטייה. she-domeh le-netiyah.
Shlomo is like a planting, he grows and he becomes you know
tall and great and flourishes, okay, במלכותו be-malchuto in his kingdom. that's
the וגדרה עם המלך Vegederah im hamelech also you have the word
מלך melech there so where were
we? וגדרה זו סנהדרין Vegederah zo Sanhedrin and fenced in this is
the סנהדרין Sanhedrin שגדרו פרצותיהם של ישראל shegidru pirtzoteihem shel Yisrael they
fenced in that's the word גדרה gidra you know the breaches of
Israel. עם המלך במלכותו Im hamelech bemalchuto
with the king in his work ישבו שם yashvu sham they dwelt
there זו רות המואביה zo Rut hamoaviyah שראתה במלכות שלמה בן בנו
של בן בנו sherata bemalchut Shlomo ben beno shel ben beno
that רות Rut you know her descendants of her descendants ultimately שלמה
Shlomo was a descendant of רות Rut שנאמר shene'emar as it says
וישם כסא לאם המלך vayasem kisse l'em hamelech so
he made a chair for the mother of the king of the
queen so this is by שלמה Shlomo so we're not going to
read it just to mean his mother ואמר רבי אלעזר v'amar Rabbi
Elazar לאימה של מלכות l'imah shel malchut it doesn't mean his mother
it means the mother of the kingship you know the ultimate the
foremother of the kingship which is which is רות. Rut. So I
don't know according to this מדרש Midrash whether it means that it
was a symbolic chair like the כוס של אליהו kos shel Eliyahu
or the כסא של אליהו kisse shel Eliyahu or does it mean
she's right? I know she says שראתה sherata
she really like saw.
Yeah right so according to this it sounds like she actually lived
that long. Right okay anyway so fine the I forget who it
is the מהרש''א Maharsha I think also points out or maybe again
it was the רב יעקב עמדין Rav Yaakov Emden piece I mentioned
before that the mention of סנהדרין Sanhedrin is cause you know it's
סנהדרין Sanhedrin according to a מדרש Midrash basically you know it's like
you know the whole thing is that when בועז Boaz wanted to
marry רות Rut all the people were saying you can't marry רות
Rut she's a Moavite and it says לא יבוא עמוני ומואבי lo
yavo Amoni u'Moavi so you know בועז Boaz basically said מואבי ולא
מואבית Moavi velo Moavit and he sort of convened a בית דין
beit din decided that that was the right interpretation of the פסוק
pasuk allowed him to marry רות Rut you know so obviously the
סנהדרין Sanhedrin sort of validated you know that interpretation as well so
also you know connecting it more directly here to the to the
רות Rut story. Okay so now continues תנו רבנן t'nu rabbanan ואכלתם
מן התבואה ישן v'achaltem min hatvuah yashan so that's sort of going
back to מחלון וכליון Machlon veChilyon and having abandoned the land and
so on and now again sort of going again to the question
about the you know about
about eating from the produce of the land and being not running
up prices etc ואכלתם מן התבואה ישן v'achaltem min hatvuah yashan so
we mentioned the idea that you can sort of store fruit for
three years when שמיטה shmitah is going to come but now we
end with the divine promise that God will make sure that you're
provided during the duration of שמיטה shmitah you'll eat from the old
grain בלא סלמותון belo salmotone without I was going to make what's
the word salmonella right I was going to make that joke salmonella
I just couldn't remember the word for it anyway but the רשב''ם
Rashbam says it means like like a rot okay or like a
type of a worm the type of natural way in which the
grain will the grain will stay for three years without without rotting
and getting wormy. מאי בלא סלמותון Mai belo salmotone what does that
mean רב נחמן אמר בלא רצינתא Rav Nachman amar belo rtzinta which
the רשב''ם Rashbam again says that means like without becoming wormy or
rot רב ששת אמר בלא שדיפה Rav Sheshet amar belo shadifa without
being like blasted right like like blasted right but
but that doesn't make so much sense after it's been harvested so
the רשב''ם Rashbam says it means that it doesn't get like warm
and I don't know what that means or
be yet like a very let's say humid kind of way
maybe yeah I guess so תני כוותיה דרב ששת tanni kavateh de'Rav
Sheshet תני כוותיה דרב נחמן tanni kavateh de'Rav Nachman תני כוותיה דרב
נחמן tanni kavateh de'Rav Nachman ואכלתם ישן v'achaltem yashan יכול ישראל מצפים
לחדש מפני
ישן שכלה yachol Yisrael mtzipim lachadash mipnei yashan shekalah so maybe fine
you'll eat ישן yashan but then you'll be anxious for the new
grain because you'll be out of the old one before the new
one comes about and they actually end of the פסוק pasuk says
not that way it says וישן מפני חדש תוציאו veyashan mipnei chadash
totzi'u but anyway but here the גמרא gemara is elaborating on the
פסוק pasuk תלמוד לומר עד בוא תבואתה talmud lomar ad bo tvuatah
no no no you will be able to wait until the harvest
the next harvest reaches its full ripeness you'll have so much of
the old grain עד שתבוא תבואתה
מאליה ad shetavo tvuatah me'eleha and what does that exactly prove that
it's like that it means it won't rot because it sounds like
the grain will no longer will be consumed so you know there
won't be any left so that would be a concern that it
would be eated and or what wouldn't be eated would rot and
it says don't worry about that תני כוותיה דרב ששת tanni kavateh
de'Rav Sheshet ואכלתם מן התבואה ישן v'achaltem min hatvuah yashan יכול ישראל
מצפים לחדש מפני ישן שרע yachol Yisrael mtzipim lachadash mipnei yashan sherah
so the concern isn't that the old one will be there won't
be enough of it it'll be rotten but it will be it
won't be as good it'll be somewhat you know it'll be less
fresh less edible תלמוד לומר עד בוא תבואתה עד שתבוא מאליה talmud
lomar ad bo tvuatah ad shetavo me'eleha fine תנו רבנן ואכלתם ישן
נושן t'nu rabbanan v'achaltem yashan noshan מלמד שכל מיושן מחבירו הוי יפה
מחבירו melamed shekol mayushan mechaveiro havei yafeh mechaveiro
so somehow the double language of ישן נושן yashan noshan means that
it actually gets better as it ages I mean that's true for
some things we normally only I think assume that that's true for
wheat but anyway ואין לי אלא דברים שדרכן לישנן v'ein li ella
dvarim shedarkam leyashnan
that's things that normally are aged and that improve with age דברים
שאין דרכן לישנן מניין dvarim she'ein darkam leyashnan minayin how do we
know that the promise here of שמיטה shmitah will be in things
that don't normally improve with age here they will get better תלמוד
לומר ישן נושן מכל מקום talmud lomar yashan noshan mikol makom
okay the double language
וישן מפני חדש תוציאו. veyashan mipnei chadash totzi'u. grain out because by
force of the new grain that's harvested. תוציאו מלמד שהיו אוצרות מלאין
ישן. totziu melamed shehayu otzarot melayin yashan.
Your warehouses will still be filled with old grain, וגרנות מלאין חדש,
v'granot melayin chadash,
and your threshing floors will be now full of the new grain
that you've just harvested. ויש לומר היך נוציא זה מפני זה? v'yesh
lomar heich notzi zeh mipnei zeh? What are we going to do?
We need to store the new grain, but we still have the
warehouses filled with old grain. אמר רב פפא כל מילי עתיקא מעליא,
amar Rav Papa kol mili atika ma'alya, all old things are good,
לבר מתמרי ושכרי והרסנא, levar mitamrei v'shichrei v'harsena,
except for dates, beer, and fish hash. I would certainly agree with
the fish hash. I'm assuming the other two are right also.
You don't buy wine hoping it's going to start turning premium for
day-old bread?
I guess, I don't know. Anyway, that was... but it was nice
to end with all this concern about cornering the market and staples
and so on, end with more of like the positive, you know,
promise about that it will be overflowing with the wheat and with
the grain and so on. הדרן עלך המוכר את הספינה. hadran alach
hamocher et hasfinah. Okay, so that was wrapping up from yesterday. Now
let's take a look now. We begin a new perek. So המוכר
את הספינה hamocher et hasfinah was a very rich perek actually, you
know, when they learn Bava Batra in yeshivas they don't learn obviously
the whole thing. There's certain perakim that they tend to select. The
third one obviously, you know, about חזקה, chazakah, there were so many
conceptual issues that came up there, and the fifth one is also
one that they learn a great deal because, you know, I mean,
there's a lot of things that we... remember we did, you know,
we did questions about how you do types of קניינים, kinyanim, about
issues about ביטול מקח bitul mekach and overcharging, you know, so there
were like a lot of also very classic types of סוגיות sugyot
there. And now here, the sixth perek of המוכר פירות, hamocher peirot,
we're going to see that also this is something that has a
lot to do like roughly within the type of מקח טעות mekach
ta'ut type of category. In some ways maybe a little bit more
concrete, you know, not in some... not as sort of I think
as directly conceptual as the fifth perek, but certainly continues to intersect
very much with those issues and certainly it starts with a very
conceptual issue. So let's take a look. המוכר פירות לחבירו, hamocher peirot
l'chaveiro, so you sell
grain, now פירות peirot again is all, you know, a wide range
of fruit including grain and whatever, to your friend, וזרען, v'zaran, and
he went out and he bought this and I was selling to
you, you know, wheat kernels, and you went ahead and you planted
them. Your intention was to buy them because you were a farmer
and you were going to plant the next year's crop. ולא צמחו,
v'lo tzamchu, and they did not sprout because guess what? I never
promised that they were able to be planted. I thought you were
going to make wheat out of them. Okay, ואפילו זרע פשתן, v'afilu
zera pishtan, even if what you bought was flaxseed and most people
buy flaxseed for the purpose of planting. Right, obviously we know nowadays,
you know, you buy flaxseed, especially the people the health type of
food or whatever, some people buy it for eating, but presumably it
was like the majority it was assumed that you'd be buying it
for
planting, and אינו חייב באחריותו. eino chayav b'achrayuto. You're coming back to
me and you're saying I want my money back. I say hey,
not my responsibility. You didn't tell me you wanted to buy seeds
for planting. I was assuming that you were going to be buying
it for eating purposes.
How do we know that it's not eating the seed? It could
be, you know, the bad years.
Okay, so תוספות Tosafot asks that question as well. תוספות Tosafot sort
of has a whole discussion about about like even if, you know,
even if it clearly was being sold as seeds to be planted,
how do you know to point to this person, you know, to
the seller, how do you know it was the seller's fault rather
than the farmer's fault? So תוספות Tosafot has that discussion. It would
be a case in which it would be obvious that they would
never fit for being
planted, okay, after they planted, not after they were planted, okay. So,
and nevertheless, hey, you know, if you want to make sure that
they were seeds that could be planted, you had to specify. Otherwise,
not my responsibility. Buyer beware. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, raban shimon
ben gamliel omer, זרעוני גינה שאינן נאכלין חייב באחריותן. zar'onei ginah she'einan
ne'echalin chayav b'achrayutan. If you buy types of vegetable seeds or you
know that are not edible, nobody buys them for eating, the only
reason they're bought is to be planted, then it is your responsibility,
right? Then what else did you think you were selling them for,
right? Of course, by context that's clear. So the חידוש chiddush though
is, is that when it's not clear, it's not explicit, and it's
not there's only one possibility, it's not the seller's responsibility. You can't
tell the seller you should have realized that was my intention. So
this gets to a classic debate that now the גמרא Gemara introduces.
So let's take a look.
So תוספות Tosafot would say that this זרעוני גינה, zar'onei ginah, meaning
we know that wasn't because of your lack of attention, it wasn't
like your...
Right, so the same point. You have to say in these cases
where you, in the last case as well when you can get
reimbursed, that it's in a context in which it's obvious. Here, if
you want to take a quick look, we'll look at תוספות Tosafot
about five lines before the lines get wide. תוספות Tosafot says like
this about eight lines says ויש לומר, v'yesh lomar, oh no, wait
a minute, אי נמי. i nami.
It's one, two, three, four, five, about eight lines before the lines
get wide it starts with the word לזריעה. l'zriah. He says אי
נמי הכא מיירי דאיגלאי מילתא למפרע שלא היו ראויים לזריעה כלל וכן
משמע בגמרא, i nami hacha mayri d'iglei milta l'mafre'a shelo hayu re'uyim
l'zriah klal v'chen mashma bagemara, etc., etc. The גמרא Gemara even asks
like maybe in the case at least where like maybe you as
the seller should even be responsible to reimburse the buyer for all
of the for all of the for all the expenses because he
put in all this money assuming that he had bought these you
know plantable seeds so it's a type of a context in which
it becomes obvious that they were never fit for that okay but
you're right even if it was even if it's known that I'm
selling it for for being for planting how do you the buyer
know to blame me for my pro for the problems and it's
maybe it's your problem maybe it's the way you handled it okay
so that would have to be the context we're talking about let's
start the גמרא Gemara רבא אמר Rava amar okay אתמר Itmar was
taught המוכר שור לחבירו ונמצא נגחן Hamocher shor l'chavero v'nimtza nagchan you
sell an ox to your friend and the normal reason people buy
and sell oxen in an agricultural society is for plowing and it
turns out that this ox is a goring ox and nobody wants
to keep it around to use it as a plowing ox and
the only thing you can do with it now is שחט shecht
it and use it for meat and the רשב"ם Rashbam says and
the גמרא Gemara makes it clear generally you know its value for
meat was less than its value for plowing רבא אמר הרי זה
מקח טעות Rava amar harei zeh mekach taus this is a false
purchase because you the context should you should be assuming that when
you're buying an ox it's fit for plowing and if not you
bought the wrong item okay it's not an אונאה ona'ah issue it's
not a question about did you pay too much or not pay
too much it's you got the wrong item right you remember before
the גמרא Gemara says you try to buy סוג א sug aleph
grain and you were delivered סוג ב sug bet you try to
buy wine you were delivered vinegar okay so also a goring ox
is not the is like you know is is like I brought
a car and it turns out oh there was no carburetor right
so it's like it's a מקח טעות mekach taus it's not an
אונאה ona'ah issue so therefore you get your money back ושמואל אמר
יכול לומר לו לשחיטה מכרתי לך u'Shmuel amar yachol lomar lo l'shchita
macharti lach no why do I have to the seller know what
your you know work with your assumptions of why you're buying it
as long as you don't specify all I did was I was
selling an ox I can say I assumed people would be buying
it for to make it into meat if they wanted to make
sure it could be used for plowing they would have had to
have asked those questions and specified so that seems to be exactly
what our משנה Mishnah is saying right so שמואל Shmuel lines up
very clearly with our משנה Mishnah but before yes חנניה Chananya it
seems like the seller
knows it's a goring ox so he would say oh I thought
yeah
but you could same could be true in our משנה Mishnah could
be that I knew that these seeds were not fit to be
planted right especially based on what we discussed before that you know
תוספות Tosafos points out etcetera that it's a case where it became
clear that we all that it's you know it was clear that
they weren't fit to be planted and I presumably knew that but
you're right I mean could maybe that could factor in but okay
by the way I should point out though מקח טעות mekach taus
is
usually although you know not about that I deceived you right even
if nobody was deceiving anybody right if I sold you the car
and it turned out like I thought it was totally fine I
had my mechanic check it out this and that I honestly did
and I didn't realize that there was some problem there like waiting
to whatever you know who knows what right that I missed so
it doesn't matter it's still a מקח טעות mekach taus מקח טעות
mekach taus isn't about deception right it's about that it was not
the object that you thought you were getting okay but anyway but
it's a good point that here clearly it feels like the owner
knew about it all right so so now that's a debate of
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel which is now the גמרא Gemara is
going to get into a question about whether הולכין בממון אחר הרוב
holchin b'mamon achar harov the fact that most people buy it for
for plowing can I use that as evidence that that's why I
was buying it and use that to therefore claim a מקח טעות
mekach taus but you know you could say it has nothing you
know you could say that it's a much more specific and local
question about who has the responsibility to clarify in a sale right
so you know who can in other cases where it's a question
of determining facts maybe we could say הולכין בממון אחר הרוב holchin
b'mamon achar harov right but in a case here where it's an
issue about like what was my intent and so on it could
be a very different type of a discussion but one minute let's
take a look at the גמרא Gemara first the גמרא Gemara wants
to know and I'll get back and I'll discuss that in a
minute but first the גמרא Gemara wants to know what are the
circumstances that this could even be an issue of a doubt so
the גמרא Gemara says ah very good לחזי אי גבי דזבין לנכסתא
לנכסתא אי לרדיא לרדיא lachzei ee gabei d'zavin l'nichtsa l'nichtsa ee l'radya
l'radya let's try to figure out who is the buyer if the
buyer is a guy that buys for for slaughtering if he's the
he's the local butcher now the רשב"ם Rashbam puts in and all
of this and I know him we're friends we know or whatever
we don't have to be friends but we're acquaintances we know one
another I know he's the butcher then that makes it implicit the
context that it's being sold for שחיטה shechita and then he might
even whatever we'll go we'll get to the and therefore he would
not have a legitimate claim that he was buying it for plowing
on the other hand if he's the local farmer then it's obvious
he's buying it for plowing there could the context makes it clear
okay so the גמרא Gemara says אי לרדיא לרדיא ee l'radya l'radya
so the גמרא Gemara could say you don't know who he is
he's a stranger but the גמרא Gemara gives a variation of that
בגברא דזבין להכי ולהכי b'gavra d'zavin l'hachi u'l'hachi he's a butcher and
a farmer he's got a side business which makes sense right or
whatever you know he's the type of a person that maybe he
who knows maybe he's a middleman who knows What? A profession?
He wants to use it sporadically.
Right,
you know, some type of a person where there's a possibility that
he has some other, he has other use for it. Okay. So
both possibilities are there or it could just be a guy who
I don't know who he is. Okay. ולחזי דמי היכי דמי, v'lechzei
damei heichi damei, let's look at how much it was paid for.
Okay, so this is the גמרא Gemara about דמים מודיעים damim modiyim
and the רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafot both say one minute. That
was discussed earlier, like when I buy a yoke and you know,
did I mean the both of the cattle or did I just
mean the yoke? And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda I think says דמים
מודיעים, damim modiyim, just look at how much he would pay for
it. And the חכמים Chachamim say אין דמים מודיעים, ein damim modiyim,
you can't look at it, the money was paid. So here it's
interesting that the גמרא Gemara assumes you can look at the money
to determine, and I'll talk in a minute about why this might
be different than those cases. But the גמרא Gemara says look, let's
just look how much was paid for it. If the guy's paying
you know ten thousand dollars, which is what you would pay for
a good plowing
cow, but for a meat cow you'd only pay five thousand, so
then he's got a good legitimate claim מקח טעות, mekach taut, give
me my money back. ולחזי דמי היכי דמי, v'lechzei damei heichi damei,
let's go see how much the money is. So the גמרא Gemara
says לא צריכא דיקר בישרא וקאי בדמי רדיא. lo tzricha d'yakar bisra
v'ka'ei bidmei radya.
Okay, basically the meat is now very expensive and right now you
know you would pay the same for a meat cow as you
would for a plowing cow. So therefore you can't look at the
money to determine. Now, by the way, the רשב"ם Rashbam says right,
yes, in general you can. By the way, the רשב"ם Rashbam says
if you could look at the money to determine,
right, so if I pay the amount for a... what was his
point? He says if I pay, like it's almost like a מיגו?
migo? No, it's almost like a ממנפשך. mimanafshach. If I paid ten
thousand dollars for a plowing cow and meat cows go for five
thousand, so then you say look, either it should have been clear
to you that I was buying a plowing cow and therefore it
was a מקח טעות, mekach taut, or if you want to claim
that no no no, we were all understood that we were buying
a meat cow, fine, then it's אונאה, ona'ah, then it's overcharging, then
give me my money back also. So there's also a way you
can do it that way, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't seem to
be sort of doing the ממנפשך, mimanafshach, just says no, the money
will say what you're buying it for and since it didn't live
up to that expectation, it's a מקח טעות. mekach taut. It says
no, you can't go, you don't have enough information based on the
amount of money that was paid for or based on the nature
of the buyer, and therefore you cannot tell by any of that
what the implied context was. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
it says just hold on let's get the case. So the גמרא
Gemara says אי הכי למאי נפקא מינה? ei hachi l'mai nafka mina?
So then who cares? So you bought something, you wanted to use
it for plowing, turns out it was a goring cow, it could
only be used for meat, but it's worth the same amount of
money, so... I understand, so just turn around and go ahead and
sell it to a butcher. You know why, so what's the big
deal? מקח טעות, mekach taut, you want your money back? So let's
say it's not מקח טעות, mekach taut, big deal, you just sell
it to a butcher and get your money back that way. The
גמרא Gemara says no, נפקא מינה לטרחא. nafka mina l'tircha. No, I
don't want to go ahead and start looking around for a butcher,
you know, I'm not in the business of selling meat cows to
butchers, I want to just get my money back and move on.
So the גמרא Gemara says now of course תוספות Tosafot points out
that it could have a נפקא מינה nafka mina that it gave,
you know, in the previous פרק, perek, that the market values changed
from the time I bought it, right? When I bought it they
were all the same, so you can't use the money to determine,
but since then you know the meat prices have gone back down
and now you know it's worth a lot less and I really
want the original money I paid back. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says so that's the issue, you can't determine based on all those
external factors, and here are the competing claims. So היכי דמי, heichi
damei, what's the case says the גמרא? Gemara? אי דליכא, ei d'leika,
now we're still not happy about like why this should matter, okay,
because why? Okay, says רב Rav says מקח טעות, mekach taut, you
get your money back. So the גמרא Gemara says even according to
רב, Rav, I can get the guy to be stuck with the
cow even though he says why מקח טעות, mekach taut, why? אי
דליכא לאשתלומי מיניה. ei d'leika l'ishtalumi minei. So I'm the seller let's
say. You say oh I wanted a plowing cow, it's a meat
cow, it's a non-cow, give me my money back. I'll say you
know what fine, I owe you your ten thousand dollars, but look
at this, I don't have any money on me, you know what
here for the מקח טעות mekach taut you give me back the
cow I owe you your money back, oh look here's a cow,
it's worth ten thousand dollars, take this instead of your money back,
because I don't have cash, I don't have cash, I can pay
you in equivalent goods.
Okay, some places I actually read once that when like people remember
way back when when like things like the Shopping Channel were just
getting started, for the old-timers in the room you'll remember, you know
it was this whole thing, so apparently the way that started once
was a certain company like was owed you know I don't know
ten thousand dollars and from a certain I don't know company that
sold I don't know what it was, hairdryers, and they the other
company was going out of business so they couldn't pay the debt,
so they just gave them ten thousand dollars worth of hairdryers, so
then they said what are we going to do with all these
hairdryers? So they went on TV and they sold it and they
said hey we could make a business doing this, that's how the
Shopping Channel got started. So anyway if you don't have the money.
You can pay your debts in kind. So if so, the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, מקח טעות, Mekach Taos, I owe you the money,
here, here's the cow back, now that we said the cow is
worth the same amount of money, take it back. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אי דליכא לאשתלומי מיניה, Ee d'leika l'ishtalumei minei, if you
can't get payment from the seller, לאכבי תורא בזוזי. l'akeiv tora b'zuzei.
So you just hold on to the cow with the money. So
what difference does it make to call it a מקח טעות Mekach
Taos or not מקח טעות? Mekach Taos? The owner can just give
you the cow as payment of your money back. So the גמרא
Gemara says, דאמרי אינשי, D'amri inshi, because people say, ממארי רשותך, min
marei reshusach, from the one who owes you money, from your debtor,
פארי אפרע, parei efra,
even like even bran you should you can be paid back. So
you can be paid back if you don't have the cash, they
can pay you back with the equivalent. So here too, the owner
would the seller would just pay the guy back with the cow
itself. No, צריכא, tzricha, you need it for a case, דאיכא לאשתלומי
מיניה, d'ika l'ishtalumei minei, that he has the cash on him. And
if he has the cash on him, you're the buyer, he's telling
you, why, just go sell it to a butcher. I don't want
to sell it to a butcher. Okay, keep the cow. I don't
want to keep the cow. You have the cash, give me my
cash back. So רב Rav says you're entitled to get your cash
back, and שמואל Shmuel says it's a מקח טעות, Mekach Taos, and
שמואל Shmuel says it's not a מקח טעות. Mekach Taos. So what's
that debate based on? So now we can find, now that we've
decided why it matters, let's talk about what the debate is based
on. So רב אמר הרי זה מקח טעות בתר רובא אזלינן, Rav
amar harei zeh mekach taos basar ruba azlinan, you go by the
majority, ורובא לרדיא זביני, v'rubba l'radya zvinay, and most people buy for
for plowing and therefore that was your assumption and you can say
מקח טעות. Mekach Taos. ושמואל אמר לך כי אזלינן בתר רובא באיסורא.
v'Shmuel amar lecha ki azlinan basar ruba b'issura. When do we go
by רוב? rov? By איסור, issur, בממונא לא, b'mamona lo, but by
ממונא mamona no, we want to try to decide like I found
a piece of meat, is it kosher or not? And nine of
the stores sell kosher, and one sells טריף, treif, I can assume
it's kosher. Okay, but if I want to decide whether I have
to give you your money back or not, we're not going to
go by רוב. rov. Now there's a lot to unpack here. Let's
start first with the debate of רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, whatever,
first I mean there's a lot of things here about how does
this fit in to issues earlier about about ארזי דדמי מודים, arzei
d'damei modim, how does this what's the issue here about whether you
pay back in kind or do you have to pay back in
cash? But let's first start with this basic debate about whether הולכין
בממונא אחר הרוב. holchin b'mamona achar harov. You know, so תוספות Tosafos
in a number of places asks like you know let this is
like
it's a little crazy to think that like what's the reason? The
normal reason given that אין הולכין בממונא אחר הרוב ein holchin b'mamona
achar harov
is
that what's the reason אין הולכין בממונא אחר הרוב? ein holchin b'mamona
achar harov? If רוב rov is a good determinant, right, so the
normal reason given is it's like a רוב rov against a חזקה.
chazaka. Here I was, I'll be the seller, Jenna there will be
the buyer. Jenna wants to say מקח טעות, Mekach Taos, give me
my money back. I have a רוב rov that proves that makes
us assume that I bought it for plowing. And I'll say, okay,
you got the רוב, rov, but I got the money in my
pocket. So it's a רוב rov against a חזקה. chazaka. Now sometimes
when we say רוב rov against a חזקה chazaka it means like
against a status quo, like like should we assume that a certain
thing, you know this meat became טריף, treif, the pot became טריף
treif or not? Well, it had a status quo of being kosher,
so we'll assume it didn't become טריף. treif. This is a different
חזקה. chazaka. This is a חזקה chazaka of possession. You want to
get cash out of my pocket, right? I have a חזקה chazaka
in the cash, המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya, you
have a burden of proof. So proof is more than just a
רוב. rov. Okay, and it has to do with the fact that
I am מוחזק muchzak in it. So that's normally why we explain
שמואל's Shmuel idea of אין הולכין בממונא אחר הרוב ein holchin b'mamona
achar harov because of the חזקה chazaka that stands against it. And
that's going to seem to be sort of how the גמרא Gemara
operates going forward. תוספות Tosafos not here, but when this סוגיא sugya
comes up elsewhere, תוספות Tosafos basically says I don't get it. So
by איסור issur as well. He says for example, like let's take
a case the גמרא Gemara says how do you know you go
by רוב? rov? And one example is, well, if somebody kills somebody
and we're going to execute the person, well, how do you know
that he the person that he killed wasn't a טריפה? treifa? You
know, and if the person he killed was a טריפה, treifa, you're
not חייב chayav in the death penalty. Or somebody basically, you know,
smites his father, you know מכה אביו ואמו מות יומת makeh aviv
v'imo mos yumos and is חייב מיתה. chayav misa. Well, how do
you know it was his father? דודאי הולכין אחר הרוב. D'vaday holchin
achar harov. Okay, so you're going to kill somebody, you're going to
execute somebody based on רוב. rov. So תוספות Tosafos says I don't
understand. If you're מוחזק muchzak in your money, you're also מוחזק muchzak
in your life, right? You would think that the burden of proof
you would need to take somebody's life would be at least as
high as the burden of proof you would need to take money
out of somebody's pocket. So how can you go by you know
what's the difference? And the answer there is probably because there are
different degrees of רוב. rov. There's a רוב rov that's like you
know sixty percent, seventy percent. Then there's a רוב rov that's like
ninety percent. Generally the way you
know conceptually it is, whatever the exact number is at ninety or
ninety-five, but a certain point where we treat it as close enough
to being assumed as being a ודאי. vaday. There's one case which
says we don't know. We really don't know what it was whether
it was this way or that way, but the principle is when
you don't know you follow the majority. Okay, there's another time which
it's so likely whether that's ninety or ninety-five we say הלכה halacha
this is defined as we know, okay? So we're going to for
הלכה... halacha... הלכתי halachic purposes assume we know who the father is.
We're going to assume for הלכתי halachic purposes he wasn't a טריפה.
treifah. It's not we don't know, but we're going by the majority.
But anyway, but that's the basic way of explaining שמואל Shmuel of
אין הולכין בממון אחר הרוב ein holchin bemamon achar harov is that
in order to take the money out of my pocket, you need
a high standard of proof. However, I should say,
you know, that that is not the only way, well, within this
issue of what was I selling, what did I mean when I
sold this and so on, we could say that it has, it's
a very local debate. It is not a general question of הולכין
בממון אחר הרוב, holchin bemamon achar harov, right? It is a very
local question of in a, in a market, right, who has the
burden to clarify what the context is? Right, so even if we
knew for sure that let's say that Jenna was buying it, we
the בית דין beis din knew for sure that Jenna was buying
it for the purpose of, of plowing, that doesn't mean that it's
my responsibility to know that. Right, and it's just a general question:
who has the responsibility to clarify, the buyer or the seller? Right,
you just make a convention and then everybody knows what the convention
is. And then from that point on, either the buyer has to
know that if he wants to get out of מקח טעות mekach
taus he's better, better make it clear, or the, or the seller
has to know if he wants to get out of מקח טעות
mekach taus he'd better make it clear, or the buyer wants to
know if he wants to make sure he's getting the right, the
right thing, he'd better clarify what purpose he's buying it for. Right,
so it could very much just be the question of within the
context of the marketplace, whose responsibility is it to clarify in cases
of ambiguity? But the גמרא Gemara makes it a bigger question of
הולכין בממון אחר הרוב. holchin bemamon achar harov. So that, and presumably
רוב נגד חזקה. rov neged chazakah. So that's one issue. That's like
the debate of רב ושמואל. Rav and Shmuel. Now, the question related
to that is, what do you do about הדמים מודיעים, hadamim modim,
right, the money will make it obvious?
So, what didn't we say earlier that the חכמים chachamim say you
don't go by money? Okay, so what do you deal with that?
Wasn't that mostly by real estate? What? When was it mostly by...?
No, it was by selling, no, it was by selling cows, do
when I sell a yoke do I mean two cows or not
two cows, or a yoke of cows, etc. So how do you
explain the difference there why there we said we don't and here
we do? So personally, right, I, you know, I, okay, so I
could have made a distinction, maybe this is too much of hair
splitting, but I could have made a distinction and said: remember, those
cases are like what object that I bought. So I said that
I was buying a yoke and you want to go ahead and
you want to say, look, I paid so much, it makes it
clear that I was buying the cow. And I said, look, you
said yoke. Yoke means yoke. Okay. Now again, maybe you overpaid and
it's מקח טעות, mekach taus, but you bought, but it's מקח טעות
mekach taus about the yoke, it's not that you bought the cow.
Right, so there it's the question about do you use the money
to determine that the words that were said mean their conventional use
or mean something that's a less conventional meaning of those words. And
then we could say, you know, again, the way I could read
all of this is just like we want to have clear rules
when it comes to commerce. So one clear rule is that like
words mean their conventional use. You don't look at external factors to
determine what the words mean. We're going to always assume they mean
their conventional use, and again, if everybody knows how to play by
the rules, it's fine. Okay. Whereas here, it was what you said.
You said a cow and you got a cow. Okay, so the
question there, you know, is like, but what can we sort of
like, we're not trying to make a word mean something it doesn't
mean. We're trying to actually say like what assumption, what purpose it
was being used for. Right, to me it seems like it's a
different type of a question. Okay, that's at least how I would
sort of frame it. רשב"ם ותוספות Rashbam and Tosafos give other ways
of explaining why it's different in terms of whatever, I don't want
to sort of get into it, it gets complicated. But anyway, but
it's worth acknowledging that here the גמרא Gemara says let's use the
money to determine, whereas earlier the גמרא Gemara says that we don't
go by the money, at least in saying whether a yoke means
cows or doesn't mean yoke. Okay, so there's ways of trying to
explain the difference. What I do want to say I think is
also interesting is this issue about, I don't want to skip over
it, this issue about what can you be have something repaid with
if somebody owes you money. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara here, so,
so תוספות Tosafos here discusses a couple of issues that are going
on. First of all, if it is, if it's the, if you
owe money to the, to a debtor, the גמרא Gemara makes it
clear, if you're a debtor you owe money to a creditor, the
גמרא Gemara makes it clear that if you've got cash, you've got
to pay cash. But if you don't have cash, you can go
ahead and pay equivalent. Okay, so the question here is, well let's
start with, maybe I'll just start with תוספות Tosafos has a couple
of variations, but I would just start at the end of this
big תוספות אי דלא לישתלומי. Tosafos i d'la lishitlumai. If you see
this תוספות Tosafos where he says like this,
line starts with the word להוציא, lehotza, one, two, three, four,
five, about ten lines from the bottom of that תוספות. Tosafos. He
says ומרגלא בפומיה דרבינו תם, umargla bepumey deRabbeinu Tam, it's a pearl
in the mouth of רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, pearls of wisdom, דג'
דינים יש. de'gimmel dinim yesh. Okay, there's three categories of whether you
have to pay back cash or not. בעל חוב... Baal chov... of
if אי אית ליה זוזי i it lei zuzei if you owe
money to a creditor לא מצי לסלוייקיה אלא בזוזי. lo matzi l'salukei
ella b'zuzei. You got to pay cash. He gave you cash, you
gotta give him back
cash. Okay,
but ולית ליה ve-leit lei but if you don't have cash on
you לא אמרין ליה זיל טרח ואייתי זוזי. lo amrin lei zil
tarach ve-aisei zuzei. We don't go to the point where we say
you have to go ahead and and get the cash. You know,
if you have cash you have to give it, if you don't
have cash you can give him you know whatever things you have
of value. Think about the fact that a normal בעל חוב ba'al
chov has liens and collects land and so on. So although your
primary responsibility is cash if you have it, if you don't have
it you can give him other things.
He says this elsewhere right?
Yeah, he this is always repeats it תוספות Tosafot repeats this a
lot. Okay,
אבל בנזיקין aval b'nizikin but if you damage his property אפילו אית
ליה afilu is lei מצי לסלוייקי במאי דבעי matzi l'salukei b'mai d'ba'ei
דכל מילי מיטב הוא כרב פפא. dechol milei meitav hu ke-Rav Pappa.
But if you damage his property since you never took cash from
him and now you might think you injured him you know you
invaded him you know maybe that creates a higher responsibility. But תוספות
Tosafot says no, if I basically I ran into his car and
I never took cash from him, I don't have to give him
back cash. I can give him anything of value. Everything is considered
you know but it's again it's quite funny like you hurt me
you have to make me whole why should I not be the
one that has to schlepp and sell your hair dryers to get
the money to fix my car, you know? But anyway, but that's
based on another גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, כרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע בפועל ke-Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua
b'po'el now interesting by a
worker אפילו לית ליה זוזי afilu leit lei zuzei even if the
employer does not have any cash אמרין ליה זיל טרח ואייתי amrin
lei zil tarach ve-aisei the worker can say you have to go
give me the cash. I mean you know you employed me and
I expect to be paid you know in cash. If you couldn't
have the cash to pay me then don't hire me. Okay, ואייתי
זוזי. ve-aisei zuzei. תנן בביה שעליה tnan b'veiya she-ali ya השוכר את
הפועל לעשות עמו בתבן ובקש ha-socheir et ha-poel la'asot imo b'teven u'v'kash
ואמר ליה טול מה שעשית בשכרך. v'amar lei tol mah she-shita b'scharecha.
You've been spending the whole day working at you know in my
straw and I say okay go take ten bales of straw home
for your fee. Okay, אין שומעין לו ein shomim lo ואפילו ve-afilu
okay and אפילו לית ליה זוזי afilu leit lei zuzei even if
you don't even if the employer doesn't have money have cash you
have to raise the cash. So it's interesting questions. I'm not sure
intuitively we would have said this. I think if there is a
sense intuitively that of all the people the worker is the one
that's most entitled to to get paid in cash. Okay, but you
know, but it seems anyway, but that's an interesting question. There's also
the issue here when the גמרא Gemara says so what's debated earlier
in the תוספות Tosafot is our case itself. Because our case is
I go to the guy who sold me the thing and I
want my money back.
The גמרא Gemara says if he doesn't have cash he can give
me equivalent. So there's a debate what does it mean he doesn't
have cash? He doesn't have the cash I gave him or he
doesn't have any cash on him? So some say it means he
doesn't have to have the cash I gave him. I paid him
cash, it's a מקח טעות, mikkach ta'ut, even if he spent that
if he has other cash he has to give me back cash.
Others say no, if he took your money and he spent it,
then he's like a מזיק mazik on your money and by if
he's a מזיק mazik on your money maybe he doesn't have to
give you back cash. It's only if he has the original cash
can you sort of like negate the whole sale and get your
cash back.
Even the money is meant to be spent.
I mean I guess not the right. Anyway, yeah, but that's when
it's specifically given as a loan. Anyway, so there's interesting questions about
when are you entitled to demand cash and when are you not.
Here the גמרא Gemara certainly says that if he has cash you're
entitled to get it back but there's a debate whether it means
the original cash or not the original cash.
Yeah, I had a couple questions. One was with the but I
thought I don't understand how he can give you that ox. That's
the whole question. Meaning they don't give at least another ox but
this is the ox that's damaged, it's damaged goods and it's not
damaged it's also what you don't want. So you also don't want
a pile full of hairblowers you know hair dryers.
No, but there's one thing to say okay at least hair dryers
are functional.
I understand that's exactly
the case of the damaging ox, it's a נגחן. nagchan. All right,
you want me to keep a מזיק mazik in my my my
oh I see that's a I mean that's an interest that's a
separate claim like like it's not just that it's worth less, it's
that it's a danger for me to keep it. It's it's a
potential liability. Okay, so that's an it's that's a different point. The
potential liability is a different point. Let me listen to this. We
got to move on.
We got to move on, but I listen to don't understand is
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel disagrees with תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma?
No, the גמרא Gemara explains that he's clarifying, but we haven't got
enough room yet.
In much of the rest of the ancient world they didn't have
this kind of case. You just sold into slavery if you didn't
have the cash.
That's a good point. All right, let's move on. Okay, so now
that the גמרא's Gemara framed it as הולכין בממון אחר הרוב holchin
b'mamon achar ha-rov and not the way I think you could frame
it as a local question of the rules and the assumptions governing
transaction, but a general question of I am trying to get money
out of you, can I use רוב rov as evidence? So then
it would be not limited to questions of transactions. Any question that
there's a dispute of fact and I'm trying to get money out
of you, can I win the case by proving it based on
רוב rov or not? And the גמרא Gemara wants to say that
that is a general debate of רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel whether in
questions about taking about your burden of proof to be taking money
out. is רוב rov sufficient, not limited to these cases of transactions.
So now we're going to bring a lot of evidence one way
or the other. Let's take a look.
מיתיבי, Meisvei, yeah. האשה שנתארמלה או נתגרשה. Ha'isha shenis'armela o nisga'resha. A
woman was divorced or widowed. והיא אומרת Vehi omeres and now she's
trying to collect her כתובה. kesubah. And she doesn't have her כתובה.
kesubah. It's a place where they don't write a כתובה, kesubah, so
the גט get serves as the כתובה kesubah document. Okay, at least
for the base. Obviously you can't prove a תוספת tosefes if there
was any amount added on, but the base she can collect with
the גט. get. And the base is 100 זוז zuz for
an אלמנה almana or גרושה gerusha when she was married and 200
זוז zuz if she was a בתולה besula when she was married.
So now the question is she's got the גט, get, she doesn't
have the כתובה, kesubah, what was her status when she was married?
והיא אומרת, Vehi omeres, she says, בתולה נישאתי, besula nisasi, I was
married as a בתולה, besula, I get 200 זוז. zuz. והוא אומר,
Vehu omer, so this has to be a case that she was
divorced, not widowed, because the husband here is talking, unless he's talking
from the grave. והוא אומר, Vehu omer,
I know, the children, right. והוא אומר, Vehu omer, and he says,
לא כי אלא אלמנה נשאתיך, lo ki ella almana nisasich, no, no,
no, I married you when you were a widow, so therefore I
only owe you a hundred. אם יש, Im yesh, so she is
trying to get money out of him, she's המוציא מחברו. hamotzi mechavero.
What type of proof does she have to bring? אם יש עדים
שיצתה בהינומא, Im yesh eidim sheyatz'sa behinuma, if there's witnesses that she
went out with הינומא hinuma which is a type of a, there's
a whole question of what it means, a canopy or a veil
or some type of a hat which would be worn that would
not have fully covered her hair. Okay, or the רשב"ם Rashbam reads
the ו vov as an or as opposed to an and, it
could be an and. וראשה פרוע, Verasha parua, her hair was uncovered.
So basically, if there's witnesses that the way she went to her
wedding, right, we might say now, was she wearing white at her
wedding? Although I don't know if that's always a determinant. But anyway,
the type of things that they did in a case of a
בתולה. besula. So she would go to her wedding and her hair
would be uncovered because she was at that stage, you know, which
is interesting, you know, or which is interesting. Does it mean a
woman who had been divorced or a widow was still covering her
hair? So that's interesting questions about that. Okay anyway, but nevertheless, or
you know, and it was with the whole entourage and the whole
type of, you know,
accoutrements that you would normally have for a first wedding. That would
be evidence that she was married as a בתולה. besula.
אז כתובתה מאתיים, Az kesubasah masayim, she gets 200. So you see,
says the גמרא, Gemara, you have to really prove it. It's not
enough to go by רוב. rov. טעמא, Ta'ama, the reason דאיכא עדים,
de'ika eidim, there are witnesses. הא ליכא עדים לא, Ha lika eidim
lo, without witnesses, no. ואמאי, Ve'amai, why? Now where's the רוב? rov?
Here's the רוב. rov. לימא הלך אחר רוב נשים, Leima halech achar
rov nashim, let's just go by the majority. ורוב נשים בתולות נישאות,
Verov nashim besulos nisa'os, most women get married when they were virgins.
Okay, that was at that time, you know, that was a nice
traditional society. Okay, so therefore, why not just go by... so you
see the גמרא Gemara thinks that this debate of רב Rav and
שמואל Shmuel is not at all limited to questions about assumptions that
business, you know, when we're doing buying and selling who has to
clarify. No, no, no. General question, if you have to prove facts,
can you prove facts based on רוב? rov? Okay, in order to
be מוציא ממון. motzi mamon. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבינא
משום דאיכא למימר רוב נשים בתולות נישאות ומיעוט אלמנות. Amar Ravina mishum
de'ika lemeimar rov nashim besulos nisa'os u'miyut almanos. Okay, true, majority get
married as virgins, a minority get married as widows or other non-virgins.
וכל הנישאות בתולות, Vechol hanisa'os besulos, now, but every woman who is
married as a virgin, יש לה קול, yesh la kol, there would
always be like a, not
rumor is the right word, a
common knowledge that that was a, that it was a first wedding.
Okay. וזו הואיל ואין לה קול, Vezo ho'il ve'ein la kol, now
this one, the fact- now how does the גמרא Gemara know it
doesn't have קול kol is a little strange, but the fact that
we had to get עדים eidim proves that there wasn't already knowledge
of the fact. Now of course what you and I would have
said and תוספות Tosafos phrase as the possibility is the עדים eidim
are proving the קול, kol, right? The עדים eidim are not directly
proving she was a virgin, they're proving that there was enough knowledge
at the time and assumption at the time. That's what all of-
I understand, that's what we would have said. That the עדים eidim
is about establishing the קול. kol. But the גמרא Gemara is reading
it that there was- this is the גמרא's Gemara answer. No, normally
you would go by רוב, rov, but the absence of a קול
kol here, people, we asked around and people said, "I don't know,
I don't remember," whatever. So the absence of a קול, kol, one
minute, וזו הואיל ואין לה קול איתרע ליה רובא, vezo ho'il ve'ein
la kol itra lei ruba, that undermines the presumption of the רוב
rov that she was a virgin. Yes, Ganna.
That this part with the קול, kol, we're talking about whether there
aren't
עדים.
eidim. Right, meaning that's what I just said, that we would have
said that the same...
if there's עדים, eidim, do we need the קול? kol?
No, I was saying that we would have normally assumed that the
point of the עדים eidim is to establish that there was a
קול. kol. Right.
Right. But if there's no עדים, eidim, maybe there isn't a קול.
kol.
If there's no עדים, eidim,
like if there's no one who's willing to come up and say
that it happened, so there clearly wasn't enough of a awareness of...
Oh, you're saying right, you're right, at this stage of the גמרא
Gemara we can still read it that way. That prior to bringing
the עדים, eidim, the רוב... rov... The reason רוב *rov* didn't work,
right, you're correct. Meaning תוספות *Tosafot*'s question and what I said is
going to be more relevant in a minute, but what you're saying
is correct. At this stage the גמרא *Gemara* could mean: Look, here's
why רוב *rov* wasn't enough. Because prior to bringing the עדים *edim*
we didn't know that there was a קול *kol* or we assumed
an absence of a קול *kol*, and the assumed absence of a
קול *kol* undermined the רוב *rov*. And the עדים *edim* established that
there was a קול *kol*. Right, that's correct. That means the absence
of a קול *kol*. Yes, you could read it that way and
that undermines the רוב *rov*. So but now the גמרא *Gemara* has
a question. No, one minute. כל הני דפסולות שיש להן קול *Kol
hanei de-psulot she-yesh lahen kol*. If all virgins have a קול *kol*,
כי איכא עדים מאי הוי *Ki ika edim mai havei*? This is
where it gets more complicated. So what that you have עדים *edim*?
But there's no מדלא קא ליה קול *mide-la ka lei kol*. Right,
this makes it clear that the גמרא *Gemara* does not see the
עדים *edim* and the קול *kol* the same thing. So what if
you have עדים *edim*? You said there was no קול *kol*, so
עדים *edim* prove some facts at that time, but nowadays nobody remembers
what it was. So it's the absence of a קול *kol*. סהדי
שיקרא נינהו *sahadei shikra ninhu*. So it's funny, you can have עדים
*edim* testifying to the fact that it was a veil and a
white and all this stuff and her hair was uncovered. Oh, but
nobody else knows about it. That means absence of a קול *kol*
means that she wasn't a virgin, and therefore it contradicts the עדים
*edim*, which is pretty amazing that absence of a קול *kol* would
contradict the עדים *edim*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says no, no, no.
The גמרא *Gemara* says אלא רוב נישאות בתולות שיש להן קול *Ela
rov nishot betulot she-yesh lahen kol*. Fine, fine. Not all virgins have
a קול *kol*. Of course it could be also there was a
קול *kol* at the time, this could have been thirty years later.
I understand. Anyway, fine. Most of the time we'll have known about
a קול *kol*. And again the גמרא *Gemara*'s making it clear here
that it seems קול *kol* separate from the עדים *edim*. Okay. וזו
הואיל ואין לה קול איתרע לה רובא *Ve-zu ho'il ve-ein lah kol
itra lah ruba*. So this one because there was no קול *kol*
and we had to resort to עדים *edim*, but the fact that-
the proof that there was no קול *kol* is we had to
resort to עדים *edim*. The גמרא *Gemara* seeing them as just distinct.
So the absence of a קול *kol* undermines the proof of the
רוב *rov*. But it's not that the absence of a קול *kol*
proves she wasn't a virgin. It just undermines the weight of the
רוב *rov*. And once you've got עדים *edim*, then that establishes that
she was a virgin. So the גמרא *Gemara* here is looking at
קול *kol* as distinct. But the basic answer to why did we
not go by רוב *rov* is it says because here sometimes you
say absence of evidence isn't evidence of absence, but sometimes that absence
undermines our ability to assume that the רוב *rov* was still- that
רוב *rov* was correct. Okay, but normally we would go by רוב
*rov*. Okay, so we will pick up tomorrow with continuing to look
at this framed in this way when the standard of proof of
המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה *Hamotzi me-chaveiro alav ha-ra'ayah* that you have to
prove something to get money out of somebody is proving it based
on רוב *rov* sufficient evidence or not. Okay. Thanks.